本期《造物小百科》……
On how it's made.
助听器
Hearing aids.
如今的助听器已经小巧到可以隐藏起来
The modern device has now become small enough to be discreet
随着科技进步，它们终于迎来了自己的春天
and with technological advances, they have at last come into their own.
三维拼图
3D puzzles.
传统消遣进入新维度
A traditional pastime enters a new dimension.
多达1500块三维拼片，可上下甚至侧向拼接
With 1500 3D pieces that fit up, down, and even sideways.
胶垫
Rubber mats.
废旧轮胎堆积如山，一直饱受诟病，这理所当然
Used tire mountains have had a bad press, and rightly so.
当然，消除废物的最好办法就是回收利用
Of course, the best way to eradicate waste is to recycle it.
还有抽水马桶
And toilets.
250年来，我们一直视它为理所当然
For 250 years, we've taken them for granted,
但你还会想用旱厕吗？
but would you still want to use a latrine?
不过首先，尽管它们优点不少
But first, despite their qualities,
自问世以来，助听器就一直不受聋人和听障人士待见
they've remained unloved by the deaf and hearing impaired since their invention.
但如今的助听器已变得足够小巧可隐蔽佩戴
But the modern hearing aid has now become small enough to be discreet
再加上科技进步，它们终于迎来了自己的春天
and with technological advances. They have at last come into their own.
无论是天生失聪，还是后天听力受损
Whether hearing impaired from birth or through loss later in life
失聪都是沉重打击，需要时间慢慢适应
deafness can be a massive blow, and takes time to adjust to.
助听器让成千上万的人能听到或多或少的声响
Hearing aids offer to thousands the ability to hear to some degree or other
但在制作之前，必须先进行听力测试
but before construction begins, a hearing test is needed.
听力计检测患者的听力，并生成报告
An audiometer tests the patient's hearing, and a report is produced.
接下来，为耳道制作印模
Next, a mould of the ear canal is made.
注入硅胶液，做出耳道印模
A silicon liquid is administered to create an impression.
等它凝固后，小心地取出
Once solidified, it's carefully removed.
这块凝固的胶块是耳道的完美复制品
This congealed mass, a perfect replica of the canal,
再浸入温蜡中，得到阳模
is then soaked in warm wax to obtain a positive imprint.
然后往容器里灌入硅胶
Then the container is filled with silicon,
它只要10分钟就会凝固
which hardens in only 10 minutes.
取出已凝固的硅胶块
The hardened silicon block is removed,
去除多余部分，只保留关键部位
And any excess eradicated, so that only the essential part is retained.
印模必须能轻松滑入耳道
The imprint must slip easily into the ear.
现在进入助听器的成型阶段
It's now the moulding stage for the hearing aid.
往模具中注入亚克力，然后放入这台紫外线烘箱
Acrylic is poured into the mould before placing it into this ultraviolet oven.
这台烘箱不发热，却能让亚克力变硬
Without emitting any heat, this oven hardens the acrylic.
此时，助听器外壳还没有装入电子元件
At this point, the raw prosthesis is without its electrical components.
这张图纸详细标出了放大器的电路
This plan details the electric circuit of the amplifier.
为音量旋钮钻孔
Holes are pierced for the volume control.
这些元件极为微小
The components are minuscule.
这就是音量旋钮
This is the volume control.
捕捉声音的微型麦克风
The miniature microphone that captures the sounds,
以及充当扬声器的受话器
and the earphone which functions as a speaker.
这根由7股导线编成的细线
This tiny braided wire of 7 conductors is soldered
用焊锡焊到放大器和外壳其他部件上
to the amplifier and other parts of the prosthesis with pewter.
电路板装入硅胶护套中加以保护
The hybrid circuit is inserted into a silicon casing which protects it.
然后把导线焊到受话器上
Then the wires are soldered to the speaker,
并检查音量旋钮是否工作正常
and they verify the proper functioning of the volume control.
助听器必须非常隐蔽
A hearing aid must be very discreet.
因此用金刚石锯片切掉多余部分
That's why they cut the excess with a diamond disc.
还用细砂纸打磨掉毛糙处
They also remove any roughness with fine sandpaper.
这里看到的孔是用来给受话器通气的
The holes we see here are used to vent air from the earphone.
用这根硅胶管制作通气孔
This silicon tube is used to make the vent.
往管中注入亚克力，形成一条通道
Acrylic is poured into the tube to form a tunnel.
用紫外线使亚克力硬化
Ultraviolet light is used to harden the acrylic.
随后取出硅胶管
Afterwards, the tube is removed.
这个孔用于固定拉线
This hole is used to position the fastener,
这根细线便于把助听器从耳中取出
a small wire which allows for the removal of the hearing aid from the ear.
然后装入电池
Then the battery is installed.
只剩下少数零件，如麦克风，还未就位
Only a few parts, such as the microphone. remain to be put in place.
随后所有零件被小心翼翼地装入外壳内部
Then everything is delicately assembled into the interior of the prosthesis.
然后把助听器两半粘合在一起
The 2 parts of the hearing aid are then glued together.
再次用紫外线使胶水固化
Again, ultraviolet is used as it hardens the glue.
用钻头切掉用于固定外壳零件的定位板
The plate used to position the prosthesis components is cut away with a drill.
随后手工打磨助听器，使其表面光滑、佩戴舒适
Then the hearing aid is manually polished to make it perfectly smooth and comfortable.
助听器外壳制作完成
The prosthesis is now completed.
还剩一个重要步骤：
There remains one important step:
检验它的电声特性
verifying its electroacoustic characteristic.
用这台分析仪验证助听器
It's with this analyzer that they validate that the
是否符合最初的验配处方
hearing aid conforms to the original prescription.
这些微型装置是改善听力的关键
These minute devices are key to improving one's sense
数字技术又正好适合这一领域
of hearing, and with digital technology perfectly suited to this field
希望未来能造出更小的助听器
hopefully even smaller units will be created.
拼图曾是周日消磨时光的传统活动
Jigsaw puzzles used to be a Sunday activity to wile away the long hours.
不过，请把那个印象忘掉
Well, put that image out of your mind,
因为如今的精密拼图可以有
because today's sophisticated puzzles can have
1500块三维拼片，可上下甚至侧向拼接
1500 3D pieces that fit up, down, and even sideways.
平面拼图人人皆知
Flat puzzles are well known by everyone,
但三维拼图则带来不同的挑战
but three D puzzles present a different challenge.
这些三维拼图诞生于电脑之中
These three dimensional puzzles are conceived within the brain of a computer.
图案转印到大印刷纸后，还需制作母模切刀
Transferred to large printing sheets, a master die must be created.
切割拼片需要锋利如剃刀的精密刀片
Precise, razor sharp blades are needed to cut puzzle pieces.
每个拼图都有独一无二的母模切刀
The master cutting die is unique to each puzzle.
工人们仔细测量，以确保套准无误
Workers measure meticulously to obtain a perfect register.
切割时模切刀绝不能移动
It's imperative that the die not move during the cutting.
任何偏差都会产生灾难性的连锁反应
Any deviation would have a disastrous knock-on effect,
所以要把模切刀牢牢固定到位
so it's firmly secured in its place.
模切刀的复制件被安装到位
A copy of the die is positioned.
这有点像是印刷母版
It's somewhat like printing the master.
再次校验对准情况，这一步至关重要，它决定了成品的质量
Alignment is again verified, a highly important step which ensures the quality of the final product.
最后，这块大金属板
Finally, this large metallic plate,
即切割底座，被安装上去
which is the cutting base, is installed.
就在这个表面上
It will be on this surface that.
母模切刀将被冲压
The master die will be struck.
测量完成后，模切板被推入到位
Once measurements are finished, the draw of the die is slid into place.
这台压力机按拼图上的图案进行切割
This press cuts the pattern as it appears on the puzzle.
印刷好的纸板一张张送入模切板
The sheets or printed cardboards go into the draw one
按母版图样进行切割
by one, where they're cut according to the master model.
在这个质检点，要检验切割的精确度
At this checkpoint, verification of the precision of the cut is carried out.
每一块拼片都必须形状准确
Every piece must be correctly shaped.
接下来是拼图的泡沫衬板
Next up is the foam support of the puzzle.
这台裁切机用于裁切聚乙烯薄膜
This guillotine is used to cut the polythene sheets
以便粘贴切割好的图案
onto which they will glue the cut images.
泡沫板送入这台覆膜机
Foam sheets are inserted into this laminator and
加热到232摄氏度
heated to 232 degrees centigrade.
印有图案的薄膜用热固性粘合剂粘到泡沫板上
The sheet with the design on it is glued onto the foam with a thermosetting adhesive.
现在把印刷薄膜贴到泡沫板上
Now they glue the printed sheet onto the foam sheet.
粘合完成后，拼图被叠放起来，进入拆料工序
Once the adhesion is finished, the puzzles are stacked and they proceed to the unbuckling operation.
通过拉拽去除多余的切料
By pulling, they remove the surplus cuttings.
同一图案在一块板上印有好几份
The same design is printed several times on a sheet,
所以必须把每个拼图分开
so they must separate each puzzle.
这道工序叫模型拆分
This step is called the reduction of the models.
现在要把拼片分离开来
Now the pieces have to be separated.
这台分件机完成这一任务，把拼片送入滑道
This decorticator handles this task and sends the pieces down a chute.
包装盒运来时已成型
Packing cartons arrive already made up,
拼片被装入盒中
and the puzzle pieces are placed in their boxes.
这里每天生产15000个拼图
15,000 puzzles are produced here each day.
自投产以来，该公司已设计出300多种不同的拼图
Since it began operations, the company has created more than 300 different puzzle models
从简单到极其复杂的图案不一而足
from simple to much more complex designs.
其中最大的拼图共有3146块拼片
The largest of them have a total of 3,146 pieces.
接下来的《造物小百科》：
Coming up in How It's Made:
废旧轮胎堆积如山，一直饱受诟病，这理所当然
Used tire mountains have had a bad press, and rightly so.
当然，消除废物的最好办法，就是把它回收制成胶垫
Of course, the best way to eradicate waste is to recycle it into rubber mats.
我们还会看看不起眼的马桶
And we look at the humble lavatory,
250年来我们一直视它为理所当然
for 250 years we've taken them for granted.
但你还会想用旱厕吗？
But would you still want to use a latrine?
广告之后再见
See you after the break.
欢迎回到《造物小百科》
Welcome back to How It's Made.
稍后，我们将看看不起眼的马桶
Later, we look at the humble lavatory.
250年来我们一直视它为理所当然
For 250 years, we've taken them for granted.
但你还会想用旱厕吗？
But would you still want to use a latrine?
但先来看废旧轮胎，数以百万计
But first, used tires, millions of them.
这些轮胎山反映了人类对道路交通工具的渴求
Mountains that reflect man's appetite for all things road-based.
垃圾填埋场是自然界的祸害
Landfills are a blight on nature,
消除废物的最好办法就是回收利用
and the best way to eradicate waste is to recycle it.
轮胎正被赋予新生，变成胶垫
Tires are starting to be given a new life as rubber mats.
这是我们对乡村的美好憧憬
This is the idyll we all have of the countryside,
但有时景色也会被破坏
but sometimes the view can be spoiled.
这一堆大约有10万个轮胎
There are around 100,000 tires in this pile.
好在这些轮胎将重获新生，变成胶垫
But thankfully these tires will have a second life as rubber mats.
这家工厂每天回收15000个轮胎
Each day in this factory, they recycle 15,000 tires.
轮胎必须被分解成小颗粒
Tires have to be reduced to little granules.
但首先，传送带把轮胎送入清洗机
but first this conveyor feeds the tires into the washer.
轮胎清洗后送入破碎机
Tires are washed and then sent to the shredder.
破碎机有两排巨大的刀齿
The shredder, with its 2 rows of large teeth,
能轻松对付卡车轮胎，把它们碾成碎块
makes short work of the lorry tyres and grinds them up into pieces.
这台破碎机每小时能破碎近1000个轮胎
This shredder is able to cut up almost 1,000 tyres an hour.
接着进行第二次破碎
Then, the shredder a second time.
用强力磁铁把金属从橡胶中分离出来，金属碎片
With huge magnets, metal is separated from the rubber and the metal pieces
会被另一家工厂回收利用
are recycled at another factory.
轮胎中的其他成分，如玻璃纤维和尼龙，也必须分离出来
Other components of the tyres, such as fiberglass and nylon, also have to be separated.
用筛分机去除剩余的杂物
A sifter is used to get out the remaining debris.
这座回收料场堆放着16吨轮胎颗粒
16 tons of tyre particles are piled up in this recycling depot,
但颗粒仍然太大，无法使用
but the pellets are still too large to be used.
它们被送入二次破碎机
They're sent to a secondary shredder,
在那里被进一步粉碎
where they'll be reduced even further.
强烈的研磨作用产生出橡胶粉末
The intense grinding action produces a kind of rubber powder.
粉末被摊铺在这些巨大的模具上
The powder is spread out on these enormous moulds.
它有7米长，1米多宽
It's 7 metres long and just over a metre wide.
随后存放在压力机的装料架中
They're then stored in this loading magazine of the press.
装满后，模具被送入胶垫压机
Once full, the moulds are sent to the rubber mat press.
在压机内，粉末要在高温下压制30分钟
Within this mat press, the powder has to be cooked at high temperatures for 30 minutes.
压制成型的胶垫经脱模装置取出，送去冷却
The cooked mat goes through the un-moulding unit before being sent off to cool.
此时的胶垫仍然非常烫
The rubber mats are still extremely hot.
用水流喷淋冷却几分钟
They're cooled with jets of water for a period of several minutes.
冷却后的胶垫现在可以送往下一道工序
The cooled mats can now be sent to the next department.
切割中心的传送带在切割前先对胶垫定位
This conveyor in the cutting centre positions the mat before it's cut.
胶垫通过振动去除多余水分
The mat is vibrated to eliminate any surplus water.
现在每张胶垫被切成3块
Each rubber mat is now cut up into 3 pieces.
切好的胶垫堆叠存放，等待发货
The cut mats are then stacked into a pile and stored before being shipped.
这里还生产挡泥板
Mud guards are also made here.
它们的制作方法与胶垫相同
These are made in the same way as the other mats.
在水中冷却后
After having been cooled in water,
趁余温尚在，通过开缺口工序去除多余橡胶
but while they're still warm, they remove the surplus rubber in an operation called notching.
这家工厂还生产硬橡胶圈
Hard rubber rings are also produced at this factory
采用相同的制造工艺
with the same fabrication methods,
原料照例是废旧轮胎
and as always, from old used tyres.
在12小时内，这家工厂至少能生产12000张
Over a 12-hour period, this facility makes no less than 12,000
用回收旧轮胎制成的胶垫
rubber mats from old recycled tyres.
这对公司来说是笔好生意
It's good business for the company,
最终对所有人也都有好处
and ultimately for everyone else too.
生活中，我们总是不自觉地忽视那些让生活更便利的东西
In life, we invariably take for granted the things that make our lives more convenient.
就拿马桶来说
Take the lavatory.
自1775年以来，冲水马桶一直没什么大的变化
Since 1775, the flushing toilet has remained. Pretty much the same.
如此寻常的器具，却承担着重任
Such a humble appliance, and such a big job to do.
在雕塑工作室的底座上，一件作品正在制作中
Based upon a plinth in a sculptor's studio, a piece of work is in progress.
不过，这可不是罗丹的作品
However, this is no Rodin.
罗丹：法国著名雕塑大师
制作马桶的第一步，是组装几块模具
The initial stage in creating a lavatory is to assemble several moulds.
每款新产品都要设计一个母石膏模
Each new product requires the design of a master plaster mould
再据此制作塑料工具模或母模
from which they will produce a plastic tool or master.
用它来制作批量石膏模
This will be used to create plaster duplicates.
马桶的石膏生产模由6块不同的分片组成
The plaster production mould of a toilet is made from 6 different segmented pieces
需要逐一拼装
which have to be assembled.
首先按精确配比混合水和石膏
The process begins with a mixture of water and plaster according to a precise recipe.
然后把石膏浆从工具模的注入口倒入
Then the liquid is poured into this filling hole of the tool.
石膏凝固后，就可以开始脱模
Once the plaster hardens, they can then proceed with the unmoulding.
用橡胶锤把石膏模与外围分离
They separate the plaster mould from the surround with
以免造成损伤
a rubber hammer so as not to cause any damage.
各分片被轻轻拼合
The pieces are gently assembled,
马桶的雏形逐渐显现
and the toilet softly takes its shape.
然后安装张紧带
Then they install tensioning straps.
在模具和张紧带之间插入小木块以增加张力
Little blocks are inserted between the mould and the strap to increase the tension.
模具很快就要注入泥浆
The mould will soon be filled with liquid,
木块可防止模具变形
and the blocks prevent any distortion occurring.
在大桶中正在调配泥浆
In massive vats, the recipe is being prepared.
这种被称为泥浆的原料由黏土和二氧化硅组成
Known as slip, this is a composite of clay and silica.
接着安装型芯，即模具的上部
Now they install the core, the upper part of the mould.
现在可以开始注浆了
They can now proceed with the filling.
这根铜制分流管连接着泥浆罐
This copper distribution pipe, connected to the tank containing the slip,
可同时向多个模具注浆
allows the filling of several moulds at a time.
每个模具大约需要20公斤泥浆
About 20 kilos of the mix per mould is required.
1小时后，泥浆已凝结到1厘米厚
After an hour, the slip has attained a thickness of 1 centimeter,
拔掉塞子，让多余的泥浆流出
and the plug is pulled to allow the excess slip to run out.
现在可以脱模取出还易碎的坯体
They can now unmold the still fragile piece.
用较稠的泥浆把这两部分粘合起来
This thicker slip is used to adhere these 2 pieces together.
他们开好孔，把整体分离开
They cut the holes and disengage the ensemble.
马桶至此成型
The toilet is now moulded.
为了获得完美的外观
Then, to obtain a perfect appearance,
要去掉粘合泥浆溢出形成的小棱边
they remove the little ridge formed by the surplus adhesive slip.
马桶先自然风干36小时
The toilet air-dries for 36 hours,
再放入温热烘干机烘干12小时
then in a warm air-dryer for 12 hours.
表面修整必须一丝不苟
Finishing must be impeccable.
他们仔细打磨表面，使其光滑如镜
They carefully sand the surface to make it perfectly smooth.
用吸尘器吸走粉尘
A vacuum cleaner draws up the dust.
再用压缩空气把粉尘和碎屑吹净
Then, with a jet of compressed air, dust and debris are blown away.
座便器随后由手工上釉
Bowls are then hand-painted.
水箱则由机器人喷涂上釉
As for the cistern tanks, they are painted by a robot.
随后卡车把各部件运往最后一道工序
A truck then carries the different parts to the final fabrication stage.
高温烧制
Baking.
马桶在这个窑炉中，在1176摄氏度的高温下烧制23小时
The toilets remain in this oven at a very high temperature of 1,176 degrees centigrade for 23 hours.
黏土和二氧化硅需要这么长时间才能烧结
It takes this long to fuse the clay and silica.
釉面变得坚硬而光亮
The paint then becomes hard and shiny,
成品焕然一新，光彩夺目
and the finished article stands proud and new.
历经4天工时、一位雕塑家和20公斤泥浆
After 4 days of labour, a sculptor and 20 kilos of slip,
这只马桶准备好履行那个我们都习以为常的职责了
the lavatory is ready to carry on its job that we all take for granted.